Wallace Berman
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
1907-1979 (bulk 1955-1979)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Wallace Berman
4.9 linear feet
The Wallace Berman papers date from 1907 to 1979 (bulk 1955-1979). The collection measures 4.9 linear feet and presents a cursory overview of Berman's career as an assemblage artist and poet. The collection contains business correspondence, letters from other artists and writers of the Beat movement, writings by others, scattered artwork by Berman, and photographs by Robert F. Heinecken.
Biographical Note
Wallace Berman was born in 1926 in Staten Island, New York. In the 1930s, his family moved to the Jewish district in Los Angeles. After being expelled from high school for gambling in the early 1940s, Berman immersed himself in the growing West Coast jazz scene. During this period, he briefly attended the Jepson Art School and Chouinard Art School, but departed when he found the training too academic for his needs.
In 1949, while working in a factory finishing antique furniture, he began to make sculptures from unused scraps and reject materials. By the early 1950s, Berman had become a full-time artist and an active figure in the beat community in Los Angeles and San Francisco. Many art historians consider him to be the "father" of the California assemblage movement. Moving between the two cities, Berman devoted himself to his mail art publication Semina, which contained a sampling of beat poetry and images selected by Berman.
In 1963, permanently settled in Topanga Canyon in the Los Angeles area, Berman began work on verifax collages (printed images, often from magazines and newspapers, mounted in collage fashion onto a flat surface, sometimes with solid bright areas of acrylic paint). He continued creating these works, as well as rock assemblages, until his death in 1976.
Scope and Content Note
The Wallace Berman papers, 1907-1979 (bulk 1955-1979), measure 4.9 linear feet and present a cursory overview of Berman's career as an assemblage artist and poet. The collection is valuable not only for its documentation of the work of Wallace Berman, but for its documentation of the California beat movement of the late 1950s through the early 1970s.
Found are numerous letters, writings, poems, and other published material which portray the thoughts, attitudes, and trends popular in a prominent underground culture which eventually led to radical changes in America and American art. The collection contains business correspondence, letters from other artists and writers of the beat movement, writings by others, scattered artwork by Berman, and photographs by Robert F. Heinecken. In addition, the collection contains files for Berman's mail art publications Semina and S.M.S. Also of note is the large volume of printed material (2.7 feet), much of it in the form of books and other published material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series which generally reflect material type.
With the exception of the letters in Series 1, each series is arranged chronologically. The original arrangement of the letters has been maintained, with a chronological arrangement of miscellaneous business letters and an alphabetical arrangement of the letters from Berman's more prominent colleagues.
Series 1: Letters, 1957-1979, undated (box 1, 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Notes from Interview, 1967 (box 1, 1 folder)
Series 3: Writings by Others, 1972, undated (box 1, 6 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, 1956-1976 (box 1, 4 folders)
Series 5: Semina, 1955-1967 (boxes 1-2, 26 folders)
Series 6: S. M. S., 1968 (box 2, 1 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1907-1976 (boxes 2-5, 2.7 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1956-1976 (box 5, 6 folders)
Series 9: Audio Tapes, 1962-[1965] (box 5, 6 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
Herms, George, 1935-; Jordan, Patricia, d. 1989; Lamantia, Philip, 1927-; McClure, Michael; Wieners, John, 1934-
Subjects-Topical:
Beat generation -- California; Photography, Artistic; Collage; Art -- California -- San Francisco Bay Area; Assemblage (Art); Assemblage artists; Poets
Types of Materials:
Works of art; Drawings; Photographs; Sound recordings
Names:
Bengston, Billy Al; Jess, 1923-; DeFeo, Jay, 1929-; Di Prima, Diane; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-; Fonda, Peter, 1940-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-; Heinecken, Robert, 1931-; Hirschman, Jack, 1933-; Hopper, Dennis, 1936-; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Meltzer, David; Miller, Henry, 1891-; Patchen, Kenneth, 1911-1972; Perkoff, Stuart Z.; Ruscha, Edward; Sherman, Donald
Provenance
The Wallace Berman papers were donated by Tosh Berman, Wallace Berman's son, in 1992.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 5282-5284. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letters, 1957-1979, undated, Series 1:; (box 1, OV 7, 0.5 linear feet)
  This series consists of miscellaneous business letters, ten letters from Berman, and letters from colleagues.
  The letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous Business Letters, 1959-1975, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Wallace Berman, 1960-1964, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Branaman, Robert, undated, (1 letter) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Collins, Jess and R. D., 1964-1965, (4 letters) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From DeFeo, Jay, 1965-1973, (5 letters) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From DiPrima, Diane, 1979, (1 letter enclosing a braid of hair) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Driscoll, Bob, 1964, (1 letter) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - [From Duncan, Robert] 1963, (1 letter) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Ginsberg, Allen, 1965, (1 letter) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Hirschman, Jack, 1967-1972, undated, (10 letters; 2 folders; see also OV 7) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Johnson, Ray, 1965-1968, undated, (9 letters) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From McClure, Michael, 1957-1971, undated, (26 letters; 3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Meltzer, David, 1970, undated, (2 letters) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Miller, Henry, 1964, (1 letter) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Perkoff, Stuart, 1973, undated, (2 letters) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - From Weiners, John, 1960-1969, (11 letters; 2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
- Notes from Interview, 1967, Series 2:; (box 1, 1 folder)
  This series consists of one folder of sentence fragements taken from a London interview of Berman undertaken by Sandrada.
  - Notes from London Interview by Sandrada, 1967 (Box 1, Reel 5282)
- Writings by Others, 1972, undated, Series 3:; (box 1, 6 folders)
  This series includes a typescripts for two manuscripts and poems by Michael McClure, David Meltzer, and John Wieners.
  - Typescript: "Eats" by Unidentified Author, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Typescript for Book Love Lion Book, by Michael McClure, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Poem by Unidentified Author, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Poems by Michael McClure, 1972, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Poems by David Meltzer, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Poem by John Wieners, undated (Box 1, Reel 5282)
- Artwork, 1956-1976, Series 4:; (box 1, OV 7, 4 folders)
  This series consists of eleven collages and nine drawings by Berman, and eight "photograms" by Robert F. Heinecken.
  - Artwork by Berman, 1956-1976, undated, (3 folders; see also OV 7) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Artwork by Others-Photograms by Robert F. Heinecken 1971 (Box 1, Reel 5282)
- Semina, 1955-1967, Series 5:; (boxes 1-2, 26 folders)
  This series consists of copies of Berman's mail art publication Semina. There are multiple copies of Nos. 1, 2, 4-8, and an envelope for No. 9. The files also contains Semina Art Gallery announcements.
  - Semina, Nos. 1 - 9, 1955-1964, (15 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5282)
  - Semina, Nos. 1 - 9 cont., 1955-1964, (10 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5282)
  - Semina Art Gallery Announcements, [1965-1967] (Box 2, Reel 5282)
- S. M. S., 1968, Series 6:; (box 2, 1 folder)
  This series consists of a copy of No. 1 of the mail art publication S. M. S.
  - S. M. S., No. 1, 1968 (Box 2, Reel 5282)
- Printed Material, 1907-1976, Series 7:; (boxes 2-5, 2.7 linear ft.)
  This series consists of clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, brochures, booklets, scripts written by Berman's colleagues, seventy-four books, and miscellaneous printed material. Exhibition announcements and catalogs for others includes a catalog authographed by Jasper Johns.
  The series is arranged as two subseries.
  7.1: General Printed Material, 1908-1976
  7.2: Books, 1907-1974, undated
  - General Printed Material, 1908-1976, 7.1:
    - Clippings, 1962-1976, undated, (13 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5282)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Berman, 1968-1975, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5282-5283)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1964-1971, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5283)
    - Brochures, 1964-1974 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Booklets, "Kolner Puppen-Theater," Vols. 2, 4, by Fritz Honig, 1908-1910 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Booklets, "Work of the Chariot," 1970 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Booklets, ["Moulin a Papier Richard de Bas in Ambert, France," 1974 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Scripts, The Beard, by Michael McClure 1965 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Scripts, The Yin and the Yang, by Don Sherman, Dennis Hopper, and Peter Fonda, 1966 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
  - Books, 1907-1974, undated, 7.2:
    The books in this subseries include works on various religions, theories, and philosophies fundamental to the beat movement. There are first edition publications by many of the movement's leaders.
    The books are arranged chronolgically.
    - Phanopoeia Pavane: Dance - Play in Verse by unidentified author, undated (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Another Academy by Charles Bukowski, undated (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Kabbalah by Rabbi Levi L. Krakowsky, undated (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Osma of Oz by L. Frank Baum, 1907 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Book of formation or Sepher Yetzirah by Knut Stenring, 1923 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Story of Modern Science by Henry Smith Williams, 1923 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Rota ou & La Roue Celeste by Enel, 1930 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Chinese Written Character as a Medium for Poetry by Ernest Fenollosa, edited by Ezra Pound, 1936 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Journal of Albion Moonlight by Kenneth Patchen, 1944 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Pictures of Life and of Death by Kenneth Patchen, 1946 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Poems 1948-49 by Robert Duncan, [1949] (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Waters Reglitterized by Henry Miller, 1950 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Howl by Allen Ginsberg, 1956 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Pearl Tears by Nickolas Logan, 1956 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Collectanea: I E Alexander, 1957 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Images de Jean Cocteau, preface de Georges Noel, [1957?] (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The Wisdom of the Kabbalah, foreword by Dagobert D. Runes, 1957 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Hymns to St. Geryon and Other Poems by Michael McClure, 1959 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Ragas by David Meltzer, 1959 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Letters by Robert Duncan, 1958 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Gallery of Women by Ruth Weiss, 1959 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - The First War Planes by William E. Barrett, 1960 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - A Correspondence of Americans by Jack Hirschman, 1960 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Wobbly Rock by Lew Welch, 1960 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Poems for Selected People by Idell, 1961 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Destroyed Works by Philip Lamantia, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - We All Have Something to Say to Each Other by David Meltzer, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 5283)
    - Robert Ronnie Branaman, 1963 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Television Decollage & Morning Glory/ 2 Pieces by Volf Vostell, 1963 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Points in Time by Zack Walsh, 1963 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Ballads by Helen Adams, illustrated by Jess, 1964 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Black Pilgrimage by Cameron, 1964 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Ghost Tantras by Michael McClure, 1964 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - The Esoteric Tarot by Simon Kasdin, 1965 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - The Process by David Meltzer, 1965 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Chinoiserie by John Wieners, 1965 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - The Hotel Wentley Poems by John Wieners, 1965 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Bruce Connor/Michael McClure, 1966 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Sapphobones by Kirby Doyle, 1966 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - A Portents Semina, Portents #6, (for Wallace Berman) By Samuel Charters, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - A Dream by Steve Elvin, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Love Dragon Poem by Michael L. Fram, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - The Soap Opera by Piero Heliczer, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - William Blake by Jack Hirschman, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Zen Love Poems by Idell, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Golden Sardine by Bob Kaufman, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Lying Together; Turning the Head & Shifting the Weight; The Produce District, & Other Places; Moving -- A Spring Poem by Ron Loewinsohn, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Business Cards by Billy Al Bengston and Ed Ruscha, 1968 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - The Finger by Bobbie Creeley, 1968 (Box 4, Reel 5283)
    - Hail Thee Who Play by Michael McClure, 1968 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Round the Poem Box; Rustic & Domestic Home Movies for Stan & Jane Brakhage by David Meltzer, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Black Alephs by Jack Hirschman, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Shekinah by Jack Hirschman, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Hymns to St. Geryon and Other Poems/Dark Brown by Michael McClure, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Gallowsongs: Galgenlieder by Christian Morgenstern Versions by Jess, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - General Principles of the Kabbalah by Rabbi Moses C. Luzzatto, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Greenspeech by David Meltzer, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Luna by David Meltzer, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Altars by Clayton Eshhleman, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Scintilla by Jack Hirschman, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Knots by David Meltzer, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - An Excerpt from "The Disconcerting Games of Vadim the Mechanic" by Ben Talbert, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Kabbala Surrealism: An Essay by Jack Hirschman, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - The R of the Ari's Raziel by Jack Hirschman, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - The Mammals by Michael McClure, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Spectral Measures on the Unit Disc by Bartholomew, 1973 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Hero/Lil by David Meltzer, 1973 (Box 4, Reel 5284)
    - Kabbalah by Charles Ponce, 1973 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - Alphabet by Stuart Z. Perkoff, 1973 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - Cantillations by Jack Hirschman, 1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - DJackson by Jack Hirschman, 1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - Igitur by Stephane Mallarme, 1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - Rare Angel by Michael McClure, 1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - September Blackberries by Michael McClure, 1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
    - Miscelaneous Printed Material, 1970-1974 (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
- Photographs, 1956-1976, Series 8:; (box 5, OV 7, 6 folders)
  This series contains photgraphs of Berman, his wife, his colleagues, the Poets' Parade, and his work Wall Painting. The five photographs of Berman show him with Artie Richer, B. Alexander, David Meltzer at Fergus Gallery, his son Tosh, and William Hillman. Photographs of colleagues include: Cameron, 1962; Richard Constantino, 1958; S. Berman and Samson de Brier, 1956; Samson de Brier, 1957; Bill Eisenlord, undated; George Herms, 1960; Louise Herms, 1958; Pat Jordan, 1960; Philip Lamantia, 1958 and 1959; Michael McClure (16 undated photographs); Artie Richer with Berman, 1958; John Wieners, 1959 and 1964.
  - Photographs of Berman, 1957-1976, (5 photographs; see also OV 7) (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
  - Photographs of Colleagues, 1956-1964, (3 folders; see also OV 7) (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
  - Photographs of the Poets' Parade, 1958, (3 photographs) (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
  - Photographs of Artwork "Wall Painting" by Berman, 1974, (2 photographs) (Box 5 (hol), Reel 5284)
- Audio Tapes, 1962-[1965], Series 9:; (box 6, 6 folders)
  This series contains twelve reel-to-reel tapes of poetry readings by Micahel McClure, David Meltzer, and Kenneth Patchen.
  - 3" reel-to-reel audio tape of unidentified poet reading words accompanied by sound effects, undated (Box 6 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - 7" reel-to-reel audio tape of poetry readings by David Meltzer and Kenneth Patchen, 1962 (Box 6 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - 3" reel-to-reel audio tape of Michael McClure reading poetry: "Marilyn Monroe, today thou hast past the dark barrier... Diving in a swirl of golden hair....;" Silence the eyes...Become the senses," 1962 (Box 6 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
  - 3" reel-to-reel audio tape of Michael McClure reading poetry ["Silence the eyes...Become the senses"] at the Lion House, San Francisco; recorded by Bruce Kansas Connor, [1965], (3 folders; 9 identical copies) (Box 6 (hol), Reel unfilmed)